Guide to the John Graves Papers
The Wittliff Collections
John Graves Papers
1920-2006
1946-2004
The Wittliff Collections
Graves, John, 1920-2013
SWWC.010
33.5 Linear Feet
49 boxes Plus oversize.
Forty-nine boxes of typescripts, galley proofs, correspondence, printed material, photographs, scrapbook material, notes, and artifacts, among other items, document almost the entire writing career of John Graves (1920-2013).
Conditions Governing Access
Some correspondence is restricted. Please contact The Wittliff Collections for more details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donations since 1988. Donors include: John and Jane Graves, Bill Wittliff, David Bowen, Dwain Kelly, and Samuel Hynes.
Biographical Notes
Born August 6, 1920 in Fort Worth, Texas, John Alexander Graves III grew up in that city until moving away to attend college in 1938. He graduated from Rice Institute (now Rice University) with a B.A. in English in 1942, then entered the Marine Corps and served in the Pacific theater until being wounded by a Japanese grenade on the island of Saipan. After the service, Graves traveled to Mexico for a few months then attended Columbia University, earning an M.A. in English from there in 1948. He began his professional writing career while still a graduate student by publishing a short story, titled "Quarry," in The New Yorker in 1947.
Graves taught English from 1948 to 1950 at The University of Texas at Austin, but left academia and Texas behind to spend a year freelance writing in New York City. From January 1953 to July 1955 he spent abroad, living mostly in Spain, including the Canary Islands for some months on a resident colony of writers and artists. During these years he wrote articles for publications like Holiday and Town and Country but also worked on fiction, including a semi-autobiographical novel, The Spotted Horse. Graves concentrated on finishing the novel after returning to the United States, but his agent rejected the final manuscript and Graves soon came to realize the novel was not publishable as a whole.
In the spring of 1957 Graves returned home to help care for his ill father. In November of that year, Graves completed a three-week canoe trip down part of the Brazos River that he feared was about to be changed forever by dams. His narrative chronicle of the trip was first published as a magazine article in Holiday, and later Graves added history, philosophy and folklore which resulted in his first major book, Goodbye to a River (1960). The book attracted national attention and critical praise for its original style. It won the Carr P. Collins Award of the Texas Institute of Letters in 1961 and was nominated for a National Book Award that year. In the meantime, Graves took a teaching job at Texas Christian University, married Jane Cole (his second marriage) and purchased the first of his limestone acres in Somervell County near the town of Glen Rose.
After three years assisting in and writing for a U.S. government study of pollution of the Potomac River, Graves returned to Texas and focused on converting his country acreage from a weekend getaway into a permanent home with a manageable farm and cattle ranch. In that time he also contributed to journals, magazines and books with introductions, articles, and essays—work that has continued to the present day. His observations and ruminations about his relationship with the land as a farmer and rancher led to the publication of his second major book, Hard Scrabble: Observations on a Patch of Land (1974). Hard Scrabble describes both the promise and adversity of country life, touching on subjects like animals, tools, construction, weather, water, ecology, agriculture, and migrant workers.
Starting in 1976, Graves again focused on life in the country in a series of essays that were published in Texas Monthly magazine. The essays examined topics such as fences, meat, tobacco, cows, chickens, dogs, and bees, and were collected and published for Graves' third major book, From a Limestone Ledge: Some Essays and Other Ruminations about Country Life in Texas (1980). Some essays follow up topics which he discussed in Hard Scrabble, but all focus on the "more or less country things which came to interest" Graves. From a Limestone Ledge was nominated for an American Book Award.
Although Graves has not published an extensive number of books, his contributions to magazines, books and anthologies spans over five decades. He has written introductions and narratives for a number of books and reports, often on Texas history and Texas environment, such as Cowboy Life on the Western Plains, Texas Heartland: A Hill Country Year and The Water Hustlers. Two of Graves' most famous magazine pieces, "The Last Running" and "Blue & Some Other Dogs," later became their own books, published first by Encino Press. Another well-received essay, "Recollections of a Texas Bird Glimpser," written for the art book, Of Birds and Texas (1986), transformed into a limited edition book, Self-Portrait, With Birds (1991).
In 1996 the University of Texas Press published A John Graves Reader, which gathered together fiction and non-fiction pieces, both published and unpublished, including a long, reworked excerpt from his failed novel, The Spotted Horse. More recently, Graves wrote text for the photography books Texas Rivers (2002) and Texas Hill Country (2003), and in 2004 Knopf published his memoir, Myself and Strangers, which focused on his years abroad as a freelance writer.
John Graves is one of the most important Southwestern writers. Three of his early short stories were collected in the O. Henry award series. He received a Guggenheim fellowship in 1963 and a Rockefeller fellowship in 1972. Numerous awards and recognitions have followed him throughout his writing career. Although he is generally considered a regional and nature writer due to his settings and subjects, his style, which incorporates fiction, folklore, autobiography, philosophy, and observation, defies provincial or topical boundaries. Perhaps the best example of this is Goodbye to a River, which has never gone out of print since first being published in 1960, and is still celebrated for its keen ruminations on the historical, attitudinal and natural worlds that intertwined around Graves as he canoed down the river.
Graves was married to the former Jane Cole of New York, and they had two daughters, Helen and Sally. John and Jane lived and worked on Hard Scrabble near Glen Rose until Graves' death in 2013.
Scope and Contents
Forty-nine boxes of typescripts, galley proofs, correspondence, printed material, photographs, scrapbook material, notes, and artifacts, among other items, document almost the entire writing career of John Graves (1920-2013).
The collection has been arranged into seven series: Writings(1946-2004, undated), Correspondence (1943-2006, undated), Institutional Activities (1960-1998), Awards and Honors (1961-2004), Personal Materials (circa 1920-2002, undated), Clippings (circa 1940-2004, undated), and Writings by Others (1942-2002, undated).
The author's original order has been maintained where possible.The collection gives an overview of Graves' literary career, and with numerous drafts of many of his books, essays and short stories, it is particularly strong in illustrating his writing process. Another strength of the collection lies in its documentation of the editorial process, illustrated by the correspondence with publishers and agents found in both the Works and Correspondence series. Numerous letters between Graves and fans, family and friends were added to the collection in 2007, making the Correspondence series at ten boxes the second most voluminous. Other highlights of the collection are personal photographs and journals in the Personal Materials series.
Related Materials
Books in the John Graves Collection have been cataloged separately.
See also the Bill Wittliff Collection, Accession Numbers 88-052, 89-023, 91-001, 91-009, 91-046, 91-128, 92-044, and 92-053 for photographs of John Graves. See 93-104 for Dorys Grover's collection of research materials on Graves and Southwestern literature. See Wittliff 98-042 for Ned Blessing television series script by WDW and Graves.
The Wittliff Collections also holds materials related to the production of A John Graves Reader, including copies of numerous works, correspondence, drafts, galleys and publicity materials in the UT Press Collection of A John Graves Reader (Collection 090).
The Harry Ransom Center at the University of Texas at Austin holds an additional 2.5 linear feet of Graves materials
Rivers in literature; Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Texas -- Description and travel; Natural history literature; Graves, John, 1920-2013
- Monographs, 1957-2004, undated
  Series Description
  The Monograph series includes research notes, typed manuscripts, galley proofs, printed materials, correspondence, and other materials chronicling Graves' literary contributions from his earliest short stories to his more recent essays and memoir. Materials from all of his books are included. Many of these materials were annotated by Graves with personal comments when he donated the materials to Bill Wittliff.
  Manuscript materials relating to the books Graves is credited as writing or co-writing make up the first series. Materials are arranged alphabetically by book title. Of particular interest in the files pertaining to his first book Goodbye to a River are photographs taken by Graves during his trip down the Brazos River, the plate proofs of the first edition, and two printed articles written before the publication of the book. There are also drafts of his second book, Hard Scrabble, and his 2004 memoir, Myself and Strangers. The materials relating to From a Limestone Ledge have to do with the publication of the book itself; materials relating to the essays that were previously published in Texas Monthly are in the following sub-series. Likewise, materials under Blue and Some Other Dogs, The Last Running, and Self-Portrait, With Birds have to do with the book versions of these writings, not the original versions, which can be found in the next sub-series.
  - Blue & Some Other Dogs, 1978, undated
    - Correspondence, corrected typescript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From a Limestone Ledge, 1978-1981
    - Publisher correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Preface drafts and content notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Typescript fragments, handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Personal manuscript copy (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Publisher's working copy (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Galley proofs (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Master galley proof (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Final galley proof (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Page proof (unbound) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Page proof (bound) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Promotion (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Reader correspondence (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Reviews (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Goodbye to a River, 1957-1991, undated
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Published pieces about the trip written by Graves (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Leftover passages and book notes (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Book design (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Plate proof (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Memorandum of Agreement for British edition (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reviews (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Senate Resolution No. 487 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Truitt correspondence (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Log for proposed movie (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Texas Book Club Edition - newsletter, correspondence, preface draft (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hard Scrabble, 1973-1976, undated
    - Photographic slides (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 'Incomplete Draft' (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Reserve copy of final draft (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - "Living with the Land," excerpt in Texas Monthly (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - A John Graves Reader, circa 1996
    - 'UTP Possibles & Leftovers' (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Final text (Box 4, Folder 9, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Last Running (Encino Press edition), 1974
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Myself and Strangers, 1994-2004, undated
    - Log entries (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, various (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Knopf (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Draft, September 2002 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Draft (3 copies), March 2003 (Box 5, Folder 7, Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Draft, June 2003 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Draft, with list of copies and final changes, June 2003 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Draft, with donation note (2 copies), June 2003 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Page proofs: "AU's 1st Pass" (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Page proofs: "Master 1st Pass" (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Page proofs: "AU's 2nd Pass" (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Page proofs: "Master 2nd Pass" (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Page proofs, January 2004 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Page proofs [Not dated or named] (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Uncorrected proof (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Knopf catalog (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Self-Portrait, With Birds, 1991, undated
    - Drafts (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Texas Heartland: A Hill Country Year, 1975, undated
    - Corrected typescripts, galley proof, marketing, copyright (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Texas Hill Country, 2003
    - Page proof (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Texas Rivers, 1997-2003
    - Color page proofs (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Corrected typescripts, correspondence, contract, royalty statements (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Reviews (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Water Hustlers, 1970, undated
    - Publisher's agreement, correspondence, map (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Galley proof (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Other Writings, 1946-2003, undated
  The Other Writings series is devoted to the many short stories, essays, book introductions, tributes, and unpublished pieces written by Graves, and spans almost six decades. This series is also the largest in the collection, filling eleven document boxes, plus oversize. The works within it arearranged alphabetically by title, usually according to the official published title, but sometimes by a book title if Graves' piece is an untitled introduction, or a draft title if the piece is unpublished. Many of these files contain correspondence, notes and research as well as typescripts and drafts. Some files also include or are limited to the publication itself that published it, or a clipping or photocopy of the published piece.
  Graves' work for Texas Monthly is thoroughly documented in this series, including the typescripts, galleys, clippings and correspondence he kept in two binders, covering ten years of published essays in the magazine. The manuscript of Graves' first published short story, "Quarry," can be found in this series, as well as one of his most famous pieces, "The Last Running," in both fiction and screenplay formats.
  - "America the Raped" - The Houston Post clipping, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Anything's a Shame" - corrected fragments, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "The Aztec Dog" – corrected typescript, carbon copy and printout, The Colorado Quarterly (summer 1960), correspondence, 1959-1991, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "The Banana Germ" - corrected typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Beekeeping essays – typescripts (2), correspondence, 1976, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "A Beginning for Something" - corrected typescripts (of two different pieces), undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Birds of Tarrant County 2nd edition forward - corrected typescript, clipping of first edition version, correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Bones for Barnum Brown book jacket comments - typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Branding Iron subject sketches – corrected typescript, notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - The Brave Bulls introduction – printout, diskette, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - "The Bright New Waters" – correspondence, typescript, research, Ford Times (November 1964) issue, 1959-1964 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Canary book beginning - fragment, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - "The Compress" and "Hot Day in the Baptist County" – corrected typescripts (2), correspondence, 1988, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - "Controlling Condensation" - Pipe Lovers issue, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Cowboy Life on the Texas Plains introduction: correspondence, contract, 1981-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Cowboy Life on the Texas Plains introduction: research, 1981-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Cowboy Life on the Texas Plains introduction: corrected drafts (3), notes, correspondence, 1981-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Cowboy Life on the Texas Plains introduction: corrected drafts (2), galleys, reception invitation, 1981-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - The Creek and the City - publication, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Cynthia Ann Porter forward – correspondence, corrected drafts (2), proofs, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Davis Birdsong and the Secretary of France" - typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Digging Into South Texas History preface – correspondence, corrected drafts (7), published version, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Don't Blame Daddy, He's Just Nervous" - notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "The Dreamer" – correspondence, typescript, Readers & Writers (May-June 1966) issue, 1960-1966 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "The Earth Remains Forever" forward - correspondence, notes, printout, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "The Emergency Stop" - typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Failure" - typescript, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "The Farthest Place" - corrected typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Fences book – correspondence, research, notes, fragments, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - "Fiddle Dance" – corrected typescripts (2), correspondence, 1960-1964, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "Field Sports - A Glance"- corrected typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "The Fire Pit" - corrected fragment, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "Firecrackers Without Synthesis" (review of Vangel Griffin) - The New Leader issue, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - "Fishing the Run": correspondence, contract, drafts, fragments, notes, 1980-1981, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "Fishing the Run": drafts, galleys, 1980-1981, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "A Fluid Kind of Southerner" - notes, corrected typescript, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 'Fragment: an ending for a story' - typescript page, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Friends of the EE. UU." - corrected typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Frontier Guns catalogue introduction - correspondence, corrected carbon copy, catalogues (2), 1964 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "The Green Fly"- photocopies of published piece (4), 1955 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Gringos in Mexico forward – corrected typescript, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 'Growing Up in Texas' piece - correspondence, corrected typescript, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - The Gulf: A Sketch with Some Somber Tints": corrected typescripts & printouts, notes, fragments, 1990, undated (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
  - Harry Jackson - A Note"- published piece, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Home Place text - correspondence, research, 1955-1962, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Home Place text - photographs, negatives, 1955-1962, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Home Place text - passages and listings, publication, 1955-1962, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Home to Candelaria" - typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "If You're So Smart Why Ain't You Rich?"- corrected typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "I'm Looking Out the Backdoor" - fragment, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - "In Avila" - typescripts (3), correspondence, 1961-1969 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "In the Absence of Horses" – correspondence, corrected typescripts, Escapade issue, 1959-1961, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "An Island Full of Noises" - corrected typescript fragments, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - 'Jamie' - corrected typescript and manuscript fragments, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "A Joy of Doubt" - corrected copy, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - "The Last Running" (short story) - correspondence, literary purchase agreement, 1958-1974, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - "The Last Running" (short story) - corrected typescript, clippings, Atlantic Monthly issues (2) and cover proof, Cavalcade issues (2), 1958-1974, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - The Last Running (screenplay) - corrected typescript and printout drafts (4), notes, 1990-1998, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - The Last Running (screenplay) - printout fragments of 5th draft, test printouts of rewrites, corrected printout fragment, 1990-1998, undated (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - The Last Running (screenplay) - first full and complete drafts (corrected printouts) (3), 1990-1998, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - The Last Running (screenplay) - second drafts (corrected printouts) (2), 1990-1998, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - The Last Running (screenplay) - third drafts (corrected printouts) (2), 1990-1998, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - The Last Running (screenplay) - fourth drafts (corrected printouts) (2), 1990-1998, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - The Last Running (screenplay) - correspondence, printout draft, 1990-1998, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - "The Laughter from the Western Shores" – corrected typescript and published piece, carbon copy revision, 1954-1962 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - "The Lost Americans" – photocopied Holiday article (2), 1954 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - "Love vs. Pedro Rakoczy"- Today's Woman issue, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - "The Meaning of Moonlight" – corrected carbon copies (2) and typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - "Mixed Signals at Roaring Valley Institute" - Esquire issue, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "A Need for Laughter" – carbon copies (2), typescript, correspondence, 1959, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - New Shelter piece – correspondence, notes, corrected typescript fragments, New Shelter pilot issue, 1979, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - 'Notes and Scraps from a Personal Journal' essay, 1946-1956 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted.
  - 'Odd Spain & Europe Scraps' – typescript fragments and drafts, notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - "The Off-Season" – carbon copy, galleys, Stateside issue, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Oil Notes introduction - correspondence, printout, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - "The Old Country" - photocopy of published piece, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - "The Other Texas Frontier" – correspondence, fragments, typescripts (2), 1984 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - "Our Own Piece of Country" – correspondence, corrected printouts (3) and proofs (2), 1996-1998, undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - "The Overlap Land" – photocopy of article in Holiday, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - "Paw Prints" - log, correspondence, printout, page proof (copy), 1996 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - "Paw Prints" - inscribed posters (2), 1996 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - 'People' – manuscript/typescript character sketches and notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Poetry - correspondence, typescripts, 1959, undated (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - "Quarry" - correspondence, carbon copy typescript, New Yorker issue, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - 'Range Goats' piece – correspondence, corrected typescripts (2) and fragments, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - "Recollections of a Texas Bird Glimpser" - correspondence, log, notes, book review by Graves, Author-Publisher Agreement, marketing (Of Birds and Texas), 1981-1985, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - "Recollections of a Texas Bird Glimpser" - corrected fragments and miscellaneous pages, 1981-1985, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - "Recollections of a Texas Bird Glimpser"- first and second full drafts, 1981-1985, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - "Recollections of a Texas Bird Glimpser" - corrected typescript of Of Birds and Texas, corrected typescript of essay, final version of essay, 1981-1985, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)